Preliminary Inventory of the Cleveland Public Library Collection, 1915-1946
Hoover Institution Archives
Cleveland Public Library Collection,
1915-1946
90001
1 manuscript box, 18 oversize boxes (13 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Serial issues, broadsides, handbills, and pamphlets, mainly issued by resistance groups in Belgium, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, France, Italy, Poland, Yugoslavia, and other German-occupied countries during World War II. Includes some issuances of anti-German groups in exile, some issuances of American occupation forces in Germany at the end of World War II, and a few World War I items. Some items are photographic reproductions. Collected by the War Library of the Cleveland Public Library.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Serial issues, broadsides, handbills, and pamphlets, mainly issued by resistance groups in Belgium, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, France, Italy, Poland, Yugoslavia, and other German-occupied countries during World War II. Includes some issuances of anti-German groups in exile, some issuances of American occupation forces in Germany at the end of World War II, and a few World War I items. Some items are photographic reproductions. Collected by the War Library of the Cleveland Public Library.
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Czechoslovakia.; World War, 1939-1945--Denmark.; World War, 1939-1945--Italy.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Germany--History--1945-1955.; World War, 1939-1945.; Military government.; World War, 1914-1918.; Belgium.; Czechoslovakia.; Denmark.; France.; Italy.; Poland.; Yugoslavia.; Germany.; United States--Armed Forces.; Cleveland Public Library.
Container List
- Argentina. Miscellaneous serial issues and handbills (Box 1)
- Belgium/Luxembourg
  - De Kansen zijn voor goed gekeerd
  - La Voix du Luxembourg
- Czechoslovakia
  - Cechoslovak Nezavisly Tydenik
  - Ceskoslovensky Boj
  - Hlas Naroca Ceskoslovenskeho
  - Lidove Noviny
  - Lidovy Denik
  - Narodni Politika
  - Narodni Prace
  - Ozveny
  - Prager Illustrierte
  - Pritomnost
  - Spirit of Czechoslovakia
  - Valka v Obrazech
  - Vboj
  - Vecerni Ceske Slovo
  - Vecerni Moravska Orlice
  - Venkov
- Denmark
  - Budstikken Gaar
  - Den Danske Parole
  - Danske Tidende
  - De Frie Danske
  - Morgenbladet
  - Niels Jydes Breve
  - Svensk Udgave af Information-Nordisk Nyhedstjeneste (al offentlig gengivelse forbeholdt Dansk Presse Tjeneste)
  - Tysk Dodslejr
  - Vi Danske
  - Miscellaneous handbills
- Germany (Box 2)
  - American Views
  - Dog Tag
  - Economics
  - Facts in Review
  - News from Germany
  - News of Germany
  - OK (Oversea Kid)
  - SHAEFer (Supreme Headquarters, Allied Expeditionary Force)
  - Miscellaneous handbills
- Italy (Box 3)
  - La Assegna
  - L'Azione: Alba Repubblicana
  - L'Azione: Edizione meridionale dell'Italia libera
  - L'Azione Socialista
  - Avanti!
  - Bandiera Rossa: Organo del Movimento comunista italiano
  - Bandiera Rossa: Organo del Partito socialista rivoluzionario italiano
  - Battaglie Sindacali
  - Buona Guardia
  - Cantachiaro
  - Cimento
  - Civilta Proletaria
  - Il Corriere
  - Corriere Finanziario
  - Corriere del Sud (Box 4)
  - Corriere di Roma
  - Corriere di Sicilia
  - Corriere Letterario
  - Crepuscolo
  - L'Idea
  - Ilbecco Giallo
  - Risorgimento
  - L'Unione
  - L'Unita
  - Unita Proletaria
- Hungary (Box 5)
  - Amainap
  - Esti Ujsag
  - Fuggetlen Magyarorszag
  - Magyarorszag
- Lithuania
  - J Lajsve
  - Nepriklausoma Lietuva
- Yugoslavia
  - Glasnik
  - Jutro
  - Mi Mladi
  - Nasa Pesem
  - Osvobodilna Fronta
  - Slobodna Dalmacija
  - Slovenci!
  - Slovenia in Evropa
  - Slovenska Zaveza
  - Slovenski Porocevalec
  - Svoboda ali Smrt
  - Svobodna Slovenia
  - Titov Naprijed
- Belgium (Box 6)
- France (Box 7-12)
  - L'Ecole Laique, October 1, 1942, No. 17; June 15, 1943, No. 22; October 1943, No. 25; January 1944, No. 24, March 1944, No. 25 (Box 7)
    January 1944, No. 24 (article on boycotting a French history text "France, des origins ànos jours, par Bernard FAY, Malle MAUREL, Jean EGUY, edited by de Gigord
  - L'Ecole Liberatrice: Organe du syndicat national des instituteurs (reconstitué clandestinement), Feb 1944, No. 1 (Box 7)
  - L'Ecran Français: Organe des comités du cinéma du front national de lutte pour la liberation, Dec 1943, No. 1 (Box 7)
    "Le cinema au combat, La censure, Quand les requins se mangent"
  - L'Effort: "L'Avenir" de L'Ouvrier (?), 21 March 1944, No. 1 (Box 7)
    (jokes, passage on Hitler as Stalin, Goebbels and Hitler in an airplane over France)
  - En Avant: Edité par la Fédération du Centre du parti communiste, No. 7, undated) (Box 7)
    "Le Paper, ne critique pas le prix, 1.00"
  - L'Enchainé: Special edition of northern regions and of pas-de-calais (partie communiste français), Oct-43 (Box 7)
  - L'Espoir: Organe du Parti Socialiste, Le Populaire du Sud-Est, 1943 (Box 7)
  - Essor: L'avenir de l'étudiant, No. 1-2, December 1943 (Box 7)
  - L'Est-Libre: Organe du Front National de lutte pour l'independance de la france (special issue), 14-Jul-43 (Box 7)
    (passage from Marseillaise (Quoi ! des cohortes étrangères...) and Chant du Départ (De Bara, de Viala... pour elle un Français doit mourir !), letter to Catholic youth, movements of the Franc-Tireurs, flight from working for Germany
  - L'Etincelle: Organe Régional du Parti Communiste Français), Bourgogne, Bresse, Franche-Comté, Revermont, Dombes, Bugey, Beaujolais, Jan-Feb 1944, No. 5 (Box 7)
  - Les Etoiles, August 1943 No. 10, September 1943 No. 11 (Box 7)
    August 1943 No. 10 (article on death of NRF, quote by Decour), September 1943 No. 11 (interpretation of Marseillaise, bibliography) Le crime contre l'estprit, l'honneur des poètes, la France) October 1943 No. 12, December 1943 No. 14, February 1944, No. 16 (passage on Nantua-Oyonnax)
  - L'Etudiant Patriote: Edité par le Comité National des Etudiants Français, March 1943, No. 3 (Box 7)
  - L'Eveil du XXe: Organe de la section du XXe du Parti communiste, 20-Feb-41 (Box 7)
  - L'Ex «KG »: Journal de combat des prisonniers libérés, Sep-43 (Box 7)
  - L'Example de la Corse, circa September 1943 (Box 7)
  - La Femme D'Eure et Loir: Le Journal des femmes patriotes d'Eure et Loir, Sep-43 (Box 7)
  - La Femme Comtoise: Organe de l'Union des Femmes pour la défense de la maille et la libération de la Patrie, Aug 1943, No. 2 (Box 7)
  - Femmes Françaises: Edited by «France d'Abord », Jan 1944, No. 1 (Box 7)
  - Femmes Patriotes: Organe des Comités Féminins de la Résistance, Feb 1944, No. 1 (Box 7)
    (call to Lyonnaises workers)
  - Femmes de Prisonniers: Journal féminin du Mouvement National des prisonniers de guerre et de déportés, special issue (Box 7)
  - La Flamme: Special supplement from Résistance, 5 Feb 1944, No. 5, 2nd year (Box 7)
  - Forces Unies de la Jeunesse, June, July, August, September 1943 (Box 7)
  - Le Franc Tireur, Jan 1942, No. 1, Feb. 1942, No. 2, March 1942, No. 2, April 1942, May 1942, June 1942, July 1942, No. 9, Aug 1942, September 1942, November 1942, January 1943, No. 14, February 1943, No. 15, March 1943, No. 16, April-May 1943, January 1944 (complete) (Box 7)
    Feb. 1942, No. 2 [Général, Nous Voilà, satire w/ all verses and refrain "Marechal, halte-là!"], June 1942 [passage taken from Hindenberg «Aus meinem Leben » trad. Koeltz, Paris, 1921, p. 42, «la résistance française après la bataille de Sedan »... on Resistance]
  - Le Franc Tireur Edition du Sud-Ouest, September 1943 (Box 7)
  - Le Franc Tireur Edition de Paris: «Mensuel malgré la Milice et la Gestapo », July 1944, No. 35 (Box 7)
    July 1944, No. 35 [Poem by Hugo, Vichy vu par Hugo «Tandis que dans l'auberge ils trinquent àgrand bruit... Arrive l'Avenir, le gendarme de Dieu »]
  - Le Franc Tireur Edition Sud, Feb, March, April, June 1944, No. 28, 29, 30, 32 (Box 7)
  - Le Franc Tireur Normand et Picard, August 1943 (Box 7)
  - La France, 14 July 1943, No. 1 (1st year) 15 Aug 1943, No. 2, Sep 1943, No. 3 (Box 7)
    [review of resistance press, pictures, literature, cinema, theater and collaboration],
  - France d'Abord: Organe d'information sur le mouvement des patriotes français pour la libération du territoire, Jan 1942, May 1942, October 1942, March 1943, April 1943, No. 22, August 1943, No. 28, No. 29, November 1943, No. 38 ;Jan 1944,, No. 40, March 1944, No. 44, July 1944, No. 57, 58, 60, August 1944, no. 61, 62 (Box 7)
    May 1942 [poem by Hugo, «Réveillez-vous, assez de hontes... »]
  - France d'Abord Supplement, 5 Sept 1943, No. 32 (Box 7)
  - La France en Armes: Bulletin des officiers du Cadre de reserve des Francs-Tireurs et Partisans Français, Dec 1943, No. 1 (Box 7)
  - La France au Combat: Organe Régional du «Front National », Feb-44 (Box 7)
  - La France Combattante, No date, one page. (Box 7)
  - La France Continue..., 20 June 1941, No. 2 ;September 1941, No. 5 ;October 1941, No. 6;20 October 1941, No. 7;20 November 1941, No. 8;31 December 1941, No. 11 (Box 7)
  - La France en Guerre, 30 Jan 1944 (Box 7)
  - France Libre: Organe de la France Combattante, Mexico (in Spanish !), 26 Enero 1943, No. 102; 9 Feb 1943, No. 104 (Box 7)
  - La France Libre: Organe Mensuel du Comité Breton de la « France Libre », July 1, 1941, No. 4 (Box 7)
  - La France Libre: Organe d'union et de combat pour l'independance de la France, Aug 1941, No. 1 (1st year) (Box 7)
  - La France Unie: Organe du Front National de Lutte pour la Libération det l'Independance de la France (Région Bretonne), May 1943, June 1943 (Box 7)
  - Fraternité: Organe du mouvement national contre le Facisme et la déportation, July 1943 ;15 November 1943, No. 14 (Box 7)
  - Fraternité Zone Sud: Organe du mouvement national contre le Racisme (Special edition), July 1943; 25 September 1943, No. 10 (Box 7)
  - Front National, 10 September 1943, No. 1; Nov 1943, No. 2; March 1944, No. 3 (Box 7)
  - Le Gaulliste: Feuille Française de propagande pour le soutien de la victoire du general de gaulle et des allies, Sep-Dec 1941, No. 6 (Box 7)
  - Le Gaullois: Organe de la Résistance souriante, édité par «France d'Abord », October 1943, No. 1; November 1943, No. 2, December 1943, No. 3; January 1944, No. 4, February 1944, No. 5 (Box 7)
  - Gazette du Comité de la Libération Nationale, 10 June 1944 (Box 7)
  - L'Homme Libre: Journal des Forces Françaises de l'Intérieur, Edité par le Mouvement National des Prisonniers de Guerre et Deportes, June 1944, No. 1, 2, 4, 5, 7, 8, 15 (Box 7)
  - L'Humanité: Organe centrale du parti communiste français, (1939) No. 2, 3, 5; (1940), Aug No. 73, 75, 76, 77, 78, 79, special issue, 80, 81, 82, 83, 84, 85, 86, 87, special issue, 89, 90, 95; (1941), 97, 98, 100, 102, 105, 109, 111, 112, 113, special issue, 114, 110 ?, 121, 126, 127, 132; (1942), 163, special issue, 165, 180, (1943), 208, 211, 214, 218, 219, 221, 172, 227, 230, 233, 173, 236, 237, 240, 242, 243, 180, 245, 246, 247, 248, 249, 250, 251, 252, 252, 254, 257, 258, 185, 259, 186, 261, 188, (1944) (Box 7)
  - L'Humanité: Special numbers, (No. 122) (Box 7)
  - Action (Box 8)
  - L'Aide (Box 8)
  - Les Allobroges (Box 8)
  - Après la Resistance (Box 8)
  - L'Art Français (Box 8)
  - L'Aurore (Box 8)
  - L'Avant-Garde (Box 8)
  - L'Avenir (Box 8)
  - Bir Hakeim (Box 8)
  - Bulletin des Chemins de Fer (Box 8)
  - Bulletin d'information (Box 8)
  - Bulletin d'Information de la France Libre (Box 8)
  - Cahiers du Témoignage Chrétien (Box 8)
  - Les Cahiers de l'Union Patriotique Independence (Box 8)
  - Ceux des Maquis (Box 8)
  - La Cité Nouvelle (Box 8)
  - Combat du Languedoc et du Roussillon (Box 8)
  - Combat Edition Speciale (Box 8)
  - Combat du Languedoc (Box 8)
  - Combat (Box 8)
  - Combat (Box 8)
    Organe des mouvements de Resistance Unis
  - Combat (Box 8)
    Organe du mouvement de Liberation Française
  - Combat (Box 8)
    Organe du mouvement de Liberation Nationale
  - Combat Régional (Box 8)
  - Combat Supplément Lyonnais (Box 8)
  - Les Communistes et la Lutte Armée (Box 8)
  - Le Coq Enchainé (Box 8)
  - Le Courrier de l'Air (Box 8)
  - Courrier de l'Air (Box 8)
  - Courrier Français du Témoignage Chrétien (Box 8)
  - Défense de la France (Box 8)
  - French Papers 1 (Box 8)
    Les Documents, Services d'information de la France Libre
  - French Papers 2 (Box 8)
  - L'Echo aux Ondes, June 16, 1944, No. 20 (Box 7)
  - Independance (Box 9)
  - L'Industrie Française: Organe d'Information de l'Union des Cadres Industriels de la France Combattante (Box 9)
  - Les Informations Sociales (Box 9)
  - L'Insurge (Box 9)
  - J'Accuse: Organe de liaison des forces françaises contre la barbaraie fasciste (Box 9)
  - J'Accuse: Organe du mouvement national contre la barbarie raciste (Box 9)
  - J'Accuse: Organe du mouvement naional contre le racisme (Box 9)
  - Le Jeune Combattant (Box 9)
  - Jeune Garde (Box 9)
  - Le Jeune Patriote (Box 9)
  - Jeune Révoluion: Bulletin Révolutionnaire de la Jeunesse Française (Box 9)
  - Jeunes de Provence (Box 9)
  - Journal Officiel: De la France Combattante (Box 9)
  - La Lettre de la France Combattante: News of Fighting France at War, in English, published in London (Box 9)
  - La Lettre de la France Libre (English Edition): News of the Free French Movement (Box 9)
  - Les Lettres Françaises: Clandestine. (Box 9)
  - Libération: Chronique Alpine (Box 9)
  - Libération: L'Hebdomadaire des français libres. (Box 9)
  - Libération: L'Hebdomadaire des mouvements Unis de Résistance (Box 9)
  - Libération: L'Hebdomadaire de la Résistance française (Box 9)
  - Libération: L'Hebdomadaire de la Résistance française (Edition Z.N.) (Box 9)
  - Libération: L'Hebdomadaire de la Résistance française (Edition Z.O.) (Box 9)
  - Libération: Organe du directoire des forces de libération françaises (Box 9)
  - Libération: Organe des forces de Resistance Française (Box 10)
  - Libération: Organe du mouvement de la libération nationale de Paris (Box 10)
  - Libération: Organe des mouvements de Résistance Unis (Box 10)
  - Libération: Organe des mouvements de Résistance Unis Edition Spéciale pour la Région Lyonnais (Box 10)
  - Libération: Organe des mouvements de Résistance Unis Edition Sud. (Box 10)
  - Libération Soir (Box 10)
  - Libérer et Fédérer (Box 10)
  - Liberté (Box 10)
  - Libre France: Organe des forces universitaires de la libération (Box 10)
  - Lorraine (Box 10)
  - Lumières (Box 10)
  - M.O.F.: Mouvement Ouvrier Français (Box 10)
  - La Marseillaise: Organe du Front National ... et L'Independance de la France (Box 10)
  - La Marseillaise: Organe du Front National de la lutte pour la libération de la France (Box 10)
  - La Marseillaise: Organe du local des mouvements unis de la Résistance Française (Box 10)
  - La Marseillaise du Centre (Box 10)
  - La Marseillaise du Sud-West (Box 10)
  - Le Médecin Français (Box 10)
  - Le Mur (Box 10)
  - Musiciens d'Aujourd'Hui, February 1944, No. 8 (Box 10)
  - Notre Droit (Box 10)
  - La Nouvelle République (Box 10)
  - Le Nouvelliste:, 31-Dec-43 (Box 10)
  - Opera (Box 10)
  - Ordre du Jour (Box 10)
  - Ouvrier du Batiment et du bois (Box 10)
  - Pantagruel (Box 10)
  - Paroles Françaises (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote: Bulletin Mensuel de l'Union Française Patriotique (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote: Organe du Front national de la France combattante en Loir et Cher, May-43 (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote: Organe du Front national de lutte pour la Libération de la France (Zone Sud) (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote de l'Eure (Box 10)
  - Patriote d'Eure et Loir (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote de l'Oise (Box 10)
  - Le Patriote de Saone-et-Loire (Box 10)
  - Le Paysan Patriote (Box 10)
  - Le Père Duchesne (Box 10)
  - Le Peuple (Box 10)
  - Picardie Libre (Box 10)
  - Le Plombier-Couvreur (Box 10)
  - Police et Patrie (Box 10)
  - Le Pont: Journal de Combat de Tous les Deportes en Allemagne (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire: Organe du Comitéd'Action Socialiste (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire: Organe du Parti Socialiste (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire: Organe du Parti Socialiste (Zone Nord) (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire: Organe du Parti Socialiste (Zone Sud) (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire de Seine-et-Oise (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire: Organe du Parti Socialiste (Edition de la Région parisienne). (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire du Bas Languedoc (Box 10)
  - Le Populaire du Midi (Box 10)
  - Le Proces de Riom (Box 11)
  - Pourquoi pas nous ? (Box 11)
  - Provence Libre (Box 11)
  - Le Palais Libre (Box 11)
  - Quatre-Vingt-Treize (93) (Box 11)
  - Radio-France (Box 11)
  - Le Refractaire (Box 11)
  - Le Refractaire (Zone Sud) (Box 11)
  - Renaissance (Box 11)
  - République française: Comitépaysan du Front National (Box 11)
  - Résistance: Le Nouveau Journal de Paris. (Box 11)
  - Résistance: Organe de combat affiliéau Phoest ( ?) de L'Independence. (Box 11)
  - Le Résistance Ouvrière (Box 11)
  - La Résistance Paysanne (Box 11)
  - Revanche (Box 11)
  - Le Réveil des Commerçants et Artisans (Box 11)
  - Le Réveil: Organe du parti communiste, Section Oyonnax. 8 July 1944, no. 2 (1st year) (Box 11)
  - Russie d'Aujourd'hui: Organe de l'association française des amis de l'union sovietique (Box 11)
  - La scène française, Dec 1943, No. 1. (Box 11)
    Incorporated 1944 in Les Lettres Françaises
  - Socialisme et Liberté (Box 11)
  - Le Soir, Nov 9, 1943. (Box 11)
  - Le Soviet: Organe de la Region parisienne du parti communiste internationaliste (section française de la IVe Internat) (Box 11)
  - Sportlibre: Organe National des Sportifs Patriotes, Jan 1944. (Box 11)
  - La Terre (Box 11)
  - Le Tigre, May 5, 1942. (Box 11)
  - Le Trait d'Union: Des familles de prisonniers de guerre. (Box 11)
  - Le Travailleur Alpin (Box 11)
  - Le Travailleur des P.T.T., 1 Sep 1942, No. 2. (Box 11)
  - La Tribune ds Cheminots: Organe de la Federation Nationale des Travailleurs des Chemins de Fer (Box 11)
  - L'Université Libre: Organe des Comités Universitaires du Front National (Box 11)
  - L'Université Libre: Organe du Comité Nationale des Professeurs (Edition de la Zone Sud) (Box 11)
  - Les Usines Renalt Travaillaient pour l'Armée allemande: Les usines Renault ont été frappées (Box 12)
  - Valmy: Organe de la Résistance Française àl'oppression (Box 12)
  - Valmy: Organe du Front National pour le Limousin, le Périgord, et la Marche (Box 12)
  - Veritas (Box 12)
  - La Vérité: Organe Central du parti communiste internationaliste (Box 12)
  - Vérités (Box 12)
  - Victoire (Box 12)
  - La Vie de Front National (Box 12)
  - La Vie Ouvrière (Box 12)
  - La Vie du Parti (Box 12)
  - La Vie de la R.P. (Box 12)
  - Vive Stalin (Box 12)
  - Voix d'actualité (Box 12)
  - La Vois de la France (Box 12)
  - La Voix des Femmes de Normandie (Box 12)
  - La Voix du Maquis: Bulletin des Forces Françaises de l'intérieur du Départment de l'Ain, 8 July 1944 (Box 12)
    published freely in area that the maquis liberated.
  - La Voix du Nord (Box 12)
  - La Voix de Paris: Edité par la Région Paris, ville du parti communiste Français (Box 12)
  - La Voix de Paris: Organe des Regions Parisiennes du Parti Communiste Français (Box 12)
  - La Voix des «Stalags »: Organe de combat des prisonniers de guerre (Box 12)
- Poland (Box 13-18)